Hello again adventurers. Welcome to the third
video in this series: **Using Monero as Money**.
In this video we will be setting up a wallet,
obtaining some juicy Monero and spending it
like cash money.
So let's get going!
According to the good folks at Moneropedia,
a wallet holds the information needed to send
and receive Monero privately and securely
from the blockchain.
As with all software, you've got several great
options to choose from.
Picking the right wallet depends on several
factors, starting with your choice of hardware and operating system.
A nice list of available
wallets can be found on the GetMonero website.
In this video, we'll be using **Feather wallet
on Linux**. Grab the software on their official
site or via Github
If you've been following this series from
the beginning, please download and verify
the wallet for your OS now.
If you've just joined us and feel confused,
please start with the first video in our series:
*Importing Public Keys and Verifying Hashes*.
While Windows users will be ready to connect
right after installing Feather, Linux users
will likely need to grant permission for either
the appimage or executable as follows:
Open a terminal window and change directory
to the folder containing the file
Type `sudo chmod +x f`, then use *Tab* to
complete the line
Now you can double click on the program as
you normally would.
When Feather starts for the first time you'll
be greeted by the welcome screen with connection options.
Here's where you'll choose the Monero node
that your wallet will eventually connect to.
Ready to get going? Let's dive in!
After following all the steps in the last
video, you should be able to choose the
*Select node manually* option
By default your localhost IP address is filled
in, along with the
default port for Monero RPC's
Since we'll be using our wallet software on
the same machine as the node, we can leave
everything on the default settings for now
If you are using a different computer on the
same network, you'll need to select the local
IP address attributed to the machine hosting
the node.
This will commonly start with **192.168**
and can be found in your network settings.
To connect to the Monero daemon, you'll need
to edit the firewall rules on the machine
hosting your node. The default port for RPC's
is `18081`.
Follow the instructions from our second video
*Setting up your own Node*, for all the steps.
You don't need to edit the firewall rules
on your router yet.
If you aren't currently hosting your own node,
please select the *Auto connect* option. This
will instruct Feather to connect you to any
one of its preselected nodes.
After selecting the appropriate connection
method click *Next*
Now we're going to select how Feather will
route its network traffic.
The default settings will tell Feather to
use Tor for its functions. However if you
are using the *Auto connect option* Feather
will initially connect to a node using traditional
clearnet methods.
As mentioned in the second video in this series,
connecting to the Monero daemon over the clearnet
will reveal potentially sensitive information
to both:
the node's host and
***your Internet Service Provider (ISP)***
The tradeoff for privacy is speed. Tor network
traffic is slower and the initial synchronisation
will take a great deal longer.
That said, the default setting is to use Tor
in order to keep your Monero activities and
IP address private.
Choose *Configure manually* and then *Route
all traffic over Tor*
If you are connecting to your own local node
you may use the default settings without any worry.
However, selecting *Route all traffic over
Tor* can always be used as a fail-safe option.
This is what we will be doing here today.
Now that we've configured our network settings
it's time to move on to generating our seed
phrase. Go ahead and select *Next*.
To continue we're going to select *Create
new wallet* and then click *Next*.
Once we hit *Next*, Feather randomly generates
a list of 14 words known as a seed phrase.
Similar to the PGP standard, both private
keys and public keys have been generated during
this process. The seed phrase is an encoded
copy of our new private keys.
This seed phrase is based on the Bitcoin Improvement
Proposal (BIP), which aimed to enable storing
private keys in a more user-friendly way.
Unlike the more common 25 word phrase used
for Monero keys, this 14 word format enables
the automatic storage of another important
piece of information, the **restore height**.
The restore height is a record of when your
key pair was created. This is important for
when you want to restore your keys to a new
wallet.
For more information on the seed scheme used
by Feather, please take a look at the documentation.
You can regenerate this phrase as many times
as you like and when you're happy you should
make a record. We suggest you take the time
to write these words down on a piece of paper.
Be careful to note the order and make it legible.
If you ever lose access to your hardware and
have written your seed phrase down incorrectly,
your funds may well be lost.
Once you have recorded your seed phrase click
*Next*.
Feather will offer you the same warning
and if you're happy to continue, click *I
understand*.
We are now prompted to name our wallet and
choose the save location. I'm going to choose
the encrypted removable disk I set up earlier.
Once again, when we're happy click *Next*.
Now we need to choose a password to encrypt
our private key. This should be a strong password
regardless of whether someone else has access
to our hardware.
I'm going to be using the password generator
bundled with KeepassXC,
a password management program.
Once that's done, select *Create/Open wallet*.
As the name suggests, Feather is a lightweight
client.
Unlike the official Monero wallet, it doesn't
come packaged with the Monero daemon.
It's been built as a feature-rich alternative
which can be run from any device,
including small USB sticks.
For a full list of its features and a comparison
table check out the Feather documentation.
We won't be delving into all the options now,
so we urge you to do so
after watching this video.
To start with we're going to turn our attention
to the tool bar at the bottom of the window.
On the right, we can see our current balance
and a green circle.
Click *the green circle*.
This window shows us the node we are connected
to, the synchronisation status and some traffic
information. If all is well you should see
the phrase **`Synchronised`** and evidence
of data traffic, then click *OK* to exit.
Next, let's click the *Settings icon*. Here
we can access some of the basic options including:
preferred fiat currency, appearance, node
list and data paths.
I'm going to leave these all alone for now.
Once again, we suggest you take a good look
through the options. When you're finished
making your adjustments, click *OK*.
As you can see our current balance is `0`,
this means that we don't own any outputs on
the Monero blockchain.
Let's change that.
There are two dominant methods for acquiring
Monero: mining and trading. For the purpose
of this video we'll be trading fiat money
for Monero using a service called LocalMonero.
There are of course many other ways to trade,
if you're interested in exploring some of
them check out the GetMonero Merchants page.
We are going to access LocalMonero using Tor.
We encourage you to do the same.
If you don't already have the Tor browser
on your machine please download it now.
Remember, make sure you verify your downloads.
We're going to search for local buyers who
accept cash via mail or in person. This may
not suit everyone, however we want to maintain
our anonymity by trading with someone who
is not interested in our identity.
You will of course need an account before
trading, so click on the *Rocket ship icon*
to learn how the whole process works.
Before we go any further, we will need a destination
address for the other party to transfer funds.
To generate an address we need to go back
to Feather and click on the **Receive** tab.
At present there are two dominant types of
address used in the Monero ecosystem.
Primary addresses, which begin with the number `4`
and sub-addresses which begin with the number `8`.
These addresses are derived from your keys
and cannot be used by anyone else.
It's possible to generate many sub addresses.
This is great for increasing anonymity and
generally speaking it's good practice to use
a different sub-address for each sender.
Let's generate a sub-address now using the
*Create new address* button.
If we right-click on this new address we have
a few options, one of which is *Edit label*.
I'm going to select this option and enter
`localmonero-` followed by the user name of
the trader we will be dealing with.
Now when Monero is sent to this address Feather
will add **`localmonero-`** to the description,
making it simple to identify where the funds
have come from.
This is as far as we go in this video. When
you've completed your trade and have funds
available in your account, you can go ahead
and move onto the next section.
As you can see, we managed to complete our
first successful trade. We hope you were able
to do the same without trouble.
To continue, let's add a new tab to the toolbar.
To do so, select *View* and then *Show Coins*.
The *Coins* tab lists all the unspent outputs
which are owned by your keys.
If we right-click on this output and select
*Details* we can get all sorts of interesting
information. Here we can see the address it
was sent to, its current status, the amount
sent and blockchain height.
If we now head over to the *Receive* tab,
we can see that the address we created before
the trade has now been removed. This is a
handy feature built into Feather to prevent
address reuse.
Before we go any further, it's best that we
outline the basics of a Monero transaction.
Let's first define the term **owned output**.
Described simply, an owned output is a record
on the Monero blockchain which attributes
your keys with a specified amount of Monero.
Owned outputs can have any value, as long
as it is less than the total amount of Monero
in circulation.
Now that we have this definition, we can more
easily understand transactions. Every regular
transaction on the Monero blockchain is made
up of inputs and outputs. This diagram helps
to illustrate that.
Inputs consist of one or more owned output.
As owned outputs have fixed values, any number
of them may be used as inputs to meet the
required outputs.
For regular transactions there will always
be at least three outputs: the amounts to
be transferred, a miners fee and a term called
**change**.
Change is the remaining Monero after deductions
have been made for the specified outputs and
miner fee.
Even if there's no remainder, there will still
be an **output with a value of `0`**.
This is to make all transactions on the Monero
blockchain indistinguishable.
Monero is a privacy-preserving protocol, which
means all of this information is encoded and obfuscated.
If you're interested in more details
please visit the GetMonero library.
Now that we have some funds, let's spend them!
After all, ***Monero Means Money***.
Today, we're going to be buying a VPN subscription
for Mullvad from a proxystore by dys2p.
Buying a VPN subscription with Monero is a
great idea as not only will your IP address
be obfuscated, but also your identity if you
choose the right service.
Once again, we'll be accessing this site via
the Tor browser.
This proxystore is pretty simple to use. First
select your product, then your country,
now solve the captcha and select *Order*.
Once your order is ready, select *Pay invoice*.
This opens up a new window, which shows the
amount due and the address to send it to.
Now that we have these details we can head
back to our wallet. Select the *Send* tab
and fill in the details.
Be sure to double-check the address and amount
before selecting *Send* once more.
A new window will now open, let's select *Advanced*
and have a look at what's going on. Here we
can see the inputs, outputs and fee.
If everything looks good, we can finalise
the transaction by clicking *Send* once more.
Once the transaction has been confirmed on
the blockchain, the proxystore's web page
will update and the voucher code will be made
available.
The current average block time is around two
minutes, so you shouldn't have to wait very
long at all.
You may come across an issue with a vendor
where your purchase is not made available.
It's in this case which you need to be able
to prove that you made the transaction.
The vendor will most likely ask for a **payment
ID** and because Monero is a privacy protocol
you will also need to provide a **transaction
key**, also known as an **outproof signature**.
Feather allows us to generate formatted outproofs
rather simply. First navigate to the *History*
tab and then right-click on the transaction.
Select *Create Tx Proof* and then *Prove payment
to an address*.
Next we can select *Get formatted proof*,
which will then copy the required text to our clipboard.
We can verify this proof ourselves. Start
by selecting *Tools* and then *Verify transaction proof*.
We can then paste this information
and select *Verify*.
Anyone with access to this transaction proof
will be able to see both the receiving address
and the amount which was transferred.
You may have noticed that your balance has
been equal to zero for some time after your
transaction. There is a good reason for this.
Presently all outputs from a transaction are
locked for a total of ten blocks after their
initial confirmation. This is built into the
protocol and is required to ensure security
and stability.
This means that any change you may be owed
will be unavailable for approximately twenty
minutes after your transaction.
This is one of the major differences between
fiat money and Monero and is something that
developers hope to remove.
If you plan to make multiple transactions
in quick succession it is advisable to either
use the **pay to many function** that can
be found under the *Tools* tab or, you generate
multiple outputs.
Let's navigate back to the *Coins* tab. If
we right-click on the owned output we have
the option to *Sweep output*.
We can then select *Send to self* and specify
the number of outputs. In this case I want
to seperate this into 5 outputs, which is
equivilent to splitting a €100 note into
five €20 notes.
This is one of the only times you would use
your primary address and Feather does this
automatically. It will now generate the specified
number of outputs, with an equal amount of
Monero in each.
Upon confirming the transaction you will see
the history logged to the wallet file. Once
the transaction has been confirmed on the
blockchain the outputs will become visible
once again in the *Coins* tab.
Another way of achieving this is by creating
additional accounts.
If we once again turn our attention to the
*bottom toolbar* we will see an icon next
to the node status.
If we click on this, a new window will open
with the **Accounts Management Tool**.
You can create as many accounts as you like
as these are simply additional sub-addesses
which are grouped with a specific label.
Be warned though, names and labels are wallet
features and if you restore your keys to a
different wallet this information is not maintained.
As we have already discovered your seed phrase
is an incredibly important thing to keep safe and secure.
We also know that Feather is unique
when compared to other wallets as it records
seed phrases in 14 words.
What if we wanted to restore these keys to
a different wallet?
To access the standard 25 word phrase and
restore height we need to select *Wallet*
from the top toolbar and then *Seed*.
Once we've entered the password we will be
presented with our seed phrase.
All we need to do is select *Show 25 word
seed*. If you plan to make these keys available
in any other wallet, it would be good to write
these down as well.
When you're finished, click *OK*.
Seed phrases are not the only way to restore
access to your keys. You can also do it with
the keys themselves and interestingly you
can provide wallets with limited privileges
this way.
To view our keys, once again select *Wallet*
and then *Keys*. You will notice that there
are 5 keys in total, each of which serves
a special function.
The ones we're interested in are the **Secret
spend key** and **Secret view key**. These
keys, together with the primary address are
equivalent to the seed phrase.
With just the primary address, restore height
and view key, it is possible to create something
called a **View Only wallet**.
This kind of wallet enables you and other
parties the ability to view the history and
current funds attributed to your keys.
This feature exists because unlike protocols
which are not private by design, there is
no other way to share this information.
This is practical for many reasons including
the ability to provide financial records and
to pay your taxes.
In this video we've only covered the most
fundamental aspects of using Monero as money
and how to interact with Feather.
Nevertheless, we hope you've learnt a lot
and will now take the time to expand your
knowledge and experience.
Anyway, that's all for this video, thank you
for watching and peace be with you privacy fans.
~moneroguides